Finding Aid for Daniel R. Sivil Papers 1940-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Daniel R. Sivil Papers 1940-1993 1977-1983
Sivil, Daniel Ross, 1940-1995.
0.5 linear ft.
Daniel R. Sivil was active in the gay and lesbian civil rights and advocacy movement of the 1980s. b He was a founding member of the Michigan Organization for Human Rights and president of the Association of Suburban People, a gay-lesbian organization devoted to social and political activity. Files relating to organizational and advocacy efforts; correspondence with Henry Messer and other activists; and photographs.
0167 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Michael Perrone (donor no. 8839 ) and came to the library in March, 2001.
The collection is open for research.
Daniel Ross Sivil was born in Detroit, Michigan on June 25, 1940. He played an important role in the gay and lesbian civil rights and advocacy movement of the 1980s in Detroit, the state of Michigan, and nationally through his work in local and national gay rights organizations. Mr. Sivil was a founding member of the Michigan Organization for Human Rights in 1977. He also served three terms (1979-1982) as President of the Association of Suburban People (Plymouth, Michigan), a gay and lesbian organization devoted to social and political activity, as well as emotional support for that community. Mr. Sivil was also active with the Motor City Business Forum, the Detroit Area Gay and Lesbian Coalition, the American Association for Personal Privacy (Princeton, New Jersey), the Palmer Clinic (Ferndale, Michigan), the Virginia Gay Alliance (Arlington, Virginia), and the Gay Employment Protection Project (Washington, D.C.). He served as Chair of the Executive Committee on the Sexual Orientation Sub-Committee Family and Sexuality Task Force formed by the Civil Rights Committee of the Michigan House of Representatives (1981). He also served on the board of advisors of The Privacy Commission in 1982 (Sacramento, California). He has given public testimony in defense of gay and lesbian rights legislation to the Privacy Commission (1983), the City of Alexandria (Va.) Human Rights Commission (1985), and the Alexandria City Council (1987). Daniel Ross Sivil died in 1995 and is buried at Woodlawn Cemetery in Detroit.
The papers of Daniel Ross Sivil provide insight into the gay and lesbian civil rights and advocacy movement of the early 1980s on both a personal and professional level. Sivil's writings and correspondence with peers demonstrates the joys and difficulties of presiding over a grassroots gay and lesbian organization (including fundraising, attracting members, and competing with similar organizations) and lobbying for gay rights in general. The papers have been divided into three series; Activities, Correspondence, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Sivil, Daniel Ross, 1940-1995.; Gay activists--Michigan.; Association of Suburban People.; Gay rights--Michigan.; Gay liberation movement--Michigan.; Michigan Organization for Human Rights.; Gays--Michigan.; Lesbians--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Sivil, Daniel Ross, 1940-1995.; Gay rights.; Gays--Michigan.
Contributors:
Messer, Henry.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Activities
  The Activities (.20 linear feet) series contains information about the organizations and activities Mr. Sivil was involved with during his years in the Detroit area and also after relocating to the Alexandria, Virginia area in the mid-1980s. Materials of interest may include his testimony to the City of Alexandria Human Rights Commission regarding changes to the human rights ordinance and the need to include on the commission an individual knowledgeable about sexual orientation concerns; his correspondence and writings while president of the Association of Suburban People including his July 1980 address to the organization; and a copy of his birth certificate and handwritten resumes in the personal interests and information folder.
  - Alexandria (Va.) Gay Community Association, 1984-1986, Dan Sivil's testimony before the City of Alexandria Human Rights Commission (Box 1)
  - Association of Suburban People (ASP)
    - Correspondence and Writings, 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - Membership Directories, 1980, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Personal Privacy, 1980-1983 (Box 1)
  - Family and Sexuality Task Force, 1977-1980 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Organization for Human Rights, 1979-1990 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1979-1982 (Box 1)
  - Personal Interests and Information, 1940-1988 (Box 1)
  - Sexual Discrimination/Michigan Laws, 1977-1983 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence (.25 linear feet) series contains a mixture of personal and professional material. Folders of interest may include the correspondence to and from Henry D. Messer, M.D. This material relates the troubles of the Michigan Organization for Human Rights in the late 1980s. Mr. Sivil had left the organization at this point and moved to Virginia, but Dr. Messer was still involved with the organization and openly worried about its future in his communications with Mr. Sivil. Dr. Messer went on to become a founding member of the Triangle Foundation. Information about Mr. Sivil's personal life may be gleaned from his correspondence with Joseph M. Zendell with whom he had an intimate relationship. The complexities and eventual break-up of the relationship are well-documented in letters between the two.
  - From Alexandria, Virginia (after relocation to), 1985-1991 (Box 1)
  - Hiring MOHR Executive Director (Richard G. Anthony, Jr.), 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Political, 1979-1985 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1965-1983 (Box 1)
  - Betty Fairchild, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Michael B. Hoyt, 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - Henry D. Messer, MD., 1983-1993 (Box 1)
  - Michael J. Perrone (photographs), 1979-1993 (Box 1)
  - Joseph M. Zendell, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  The Photographs (.05 linear feet) series contains images of Mr. Sivil and his peers in both professional and personal settings. The photographs highlight some of the activities Mr. Sivil was involved with, including a committee meeting for the Sexual Orientation and Affectional Preference report. The majority of the photographs are of a more personal nature and feature Mr. Sivil on different trips (Washington D.C. and San Francisco) or with friends. The miscellaneous folder in particular includes several images documenting Mr. Sivil's personal life and relationships.
  - Dan Sivil and Michael Perrone in Washington, DC, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Photographs for ASP NewsletterMay 1979 (Box 1)
    (Al Redner, treasurer; M. Perrone, newsletter; Jim Childer; Bill M; Dan Sivil, president; Greg Butler)
  - Photographs for ASP Newsletter, negatives (Box 1)
  - Washington D.C. scenery, undated, negatives (Box 1)
  - Committee meeting for Sexual Orientation and Affectional Preference Report (Lansing, Capital Building), 1979 (Box 1)
  - AIDS Quilt in Washington D.C., 1989 (Box 1)
  - Dan Sivil in San Francisco (with unidentified individuals), undated (Box 1)
  - Elaine Noble, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
Related Materials
Researchers should note that issues of the Association of Suburban People (ASP) newsletters are also housed at the Bentley Library. Finally, those interested in additional materials on the gay and lesbian civil rights and advocacy movement may wish to consult additional collections held at the Bentley including the Triangle Foundation and the Michigan Organization for Human Rights.